Guide to the Myra Tanner Weiss Papers TAM.158
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Myra Tanner Weiss Papers
1933-1997
1952-1963
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Weiss, Myra Tanner
Nagel, Shirley
TAM.158
2.5 Linear Feet in five manuscript boxes.
Myra Tanner Weiss (1916-1997) was a socialist, feminist, and the Socialist Workers Party's vice-presidential candidate in 1952, 1956, and 1960. Together with her husband Murry she organized the School for Marxist Education in New York. The papers contain correspondence, speeches and writings and Socialist Workers Party internal documents.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by Myra Tanner Weiss and her sister, Shirley Nagel, in 1994. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1994.015, 1994.016 and NPA.1998.028.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into five series:
Series I: Personal
Series II: Correspondence
Series III: Socialist Workers Party
Series IV: Committee for a Revolutionary Socialist Party (CRSP)
Series V: Speeches and Writings
Historical/Biographical Note
Myra Tanner Weiss was born May 17, 1916. She joined the Socialist Workers Party in 1935 while attending the University of Utah. She moved to Los Angeles in the 1940s, at which time she organized agricultural and cannery workers. She also helped establish the SWP in Los Angeles where she met another party organizer, Murry Weiss [born Morris, in Chicago, September 9, 1915, son of Joseph and Freida; died December 26, 1981] whom she later married. Tanner Weiss ran for mayor of Los Angeles in 1945 and 1949. The Weisses moved to New York City in 1953 where Murry Weiss edited the Socialist Workers Party's newspaper The Militant. Running with Presidential candidate Farrell Dobbs, Myra Tanner Weiss was the Socialist Workers Party's Vice Presidential candidate in 1952, 1956, and 1960. Together with her husband she organized the School for Marxist Education in New York. Tanner Weiss left the SWP in the early 1960's because she thought the party had undergone a 'gross bureaucratization'. According to records of the New York local branch of the SWP Myra Tanner Weiss would no longer be considered a member of the Party as of October 1966. She did however remain politically active and became involved with the New York Socialist Feminists and the Committee for a Revolutionary Socialist Party (CRSP). Tanner Weiss received a masters degree in political science from New York University in 1972. She subsequently worked as a proof reader. She died on September 13, 1997.
Related Archival Materials
Tamiment's Oral History of the American Left (OH 002) contains an interview with Myra Tanner Weiss. Other institutions hold materials related to Tanner Weiss, including oral history recordings in Prometheus Research Library, New York (Myra Tanner Weiss interview 12/20/77; 2 cassettes) and Tanner Weiss's campaign literature in the Bob Chester Papers at the State Historical Society of Wisconsin, Madison, Wisconsin.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists primarily of correspondence and Socialist Workers Party (SWP) internal documents, dating mostly from the 1940s-1970s. The correspondence is mostly by Tanner Weiss and her husband, Murry, related to the SWP and family correspondence. The collection contains a significant amount of SWP internal working materials, including draft resolutions, minutes, correspondence, articles, circulars, reports, flyers, convention materials, and other ephemera documenting the SWP's politics and activities, as well as the Party's responses to splits and the formation of factions. The collection also contains internal papers and correspondence which document Murry and Myra Tanner Weiss' involvement with the Committee for a Revolutionary Socialist Party (CRSP). The collection also contains speeches and writings written by Murry and Myra Tanner Weiss. Important in the collection is the letter to Tanner Weiss from Natalie Sedova-Trotsky concerning a purported meeting between Leon Trotsky and Jack Soble in Turkey in 1931-1932.
Separated Materials
A set of Discussion Bulletins published by the Committee for a Revolutionary Socialist from 1978-1980 were separated to the library collection.
Women socialists -- United States.; Women and socialism -- United States.; Trotskyists -- United States.; Trotskyism -- United States.; Young People's Socialist League; Socialist Workers Party; Young Socialist Alliance (U.S.); Swabeck, Arne; Dobbs, Farrell; Weiss, Murry; Trotskaia, Nataliia Ivanovna, 1882-1962; Breitman, George; Cannon, James Patrick, 1890-1974; Nagel, Shirley
- Series I: Personal, 1912, 1981-1997; 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Content Note
  This series contains obituaries, photographs, and other personal and biographical materials related to Tanner Weiss.
  - Biography, 1981-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, 1912, undated (Box 1, Folder 1a)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1933-1987; 2
  This series contains correspondence by Myra Tanner Weiss and Murry Weiss, mostly to other correspondents. The bulk of the correspondence dates from the 1940s-1970s. There is also the correspondence of Myra Tanner Weiss' husband, Murry Weiss, much of which concerns his tenure as editor of the Socialist Workers Party (SWP) newspaper, The Militant. Tanner Weiss' letters and correspondence concern her speaking tours and political campaigns as SWP Vice Presidential candidate in 1952, 1956, and 1960, as well as personal correspondence with her husband and family. Correspondents include: Shane Mage, Tim Wohlforth, James Cannon, Sam Marcy, Natalie [Natalia] Sedova-Trotsky (Leon Trotsky's widow), Bert Deck, Farrell Dobbs, William Warde, George Breitman, George Clarke, Arne Swabeck, Harry Braverman, Clara Fraser, James Robertson.
  Arranged alphabetically and then chronologically.
  - Weiss Family Letters, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Murry Weiss / Myra Tanner Weiss Correspondence, 1948-1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Murry Weiss / Myra Tanner Weiss Correspondence, 1960-1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, 1933-1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence: Murry Weiss/California Third Party Movement, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Murry Weiss/Trotsky School Spring Mountain Camp - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, Jan-Jun 1956 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, Jul-Dec 1956 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, Jan-May 1957 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, Jun-Dec 1957 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters/Socialist Workers Party Membership, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Murry Weiss - Letters, 1976 -1978 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss - Letters, 1946-1949 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss - Letters, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss - Letters, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss - Letters, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss - Letters, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss - Letters, Jan-Jun 1956 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss - Letters, Jul-Dec 1956 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss - Letters, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Myra Tanner Weiss/Natalie Sedova-Trotsky, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss - Letters, 1958 -1959 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss - Letters, 1960-1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss - Letters/Socialist Workers Party Membership, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss - Letters, 1969-1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss - Letters, 1977-1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss - Letters: An Open Letter to the Socialist Workers Party, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss - Letters, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss - Letters, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss - Letters, 1983-1985 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss - Letters, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Letters: individuals, 1939-1953 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Letters: individuals, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letters: individuals, 1956-1985 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Letters, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Series III: Socialist Workers Party, 1944-1983; 3
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series documents Weiss's activities within the Socialist Workers Party; the documents, correspondence, minutes, flyers, and other ephemera chronicle the Cochranite split, discussions and debates concerning Pabloism (Michael Pablo, Michael Raptis: head of the International Secretariat), the Party's response to the 20th Congress of the Soviet Communist Party and its effect on the Communist Party USA, and consideration of the 1956 uprisings in Poland and Hungary. SWP policy and activity is also chronicled concerning the "regroupment campaign" of 1956-1958, as well as the Party's relationship to the Young Socialist League (YSL), the Young People's Socialist League (YPSL), the Young Socialist Alliance (YSA) and the Workers World Party. In addition, there is material and correspondence concerning the opposition group the Revolutionary Tendency (TR) and the expulsion from the SWP of Lynne Harper, Laurence Ireland, Shane Mage, James Robertson, and Geoffrey White in 1963.
  - Martin (Cannon): Comments on the Selection of the National Committee, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Felix Morrow: Where I Stand, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss v Los Angeles Broadcasting, Inc..., 1946 (Box 3, Folder 2a)
  - Socialist Workers Party Internal Documents, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Natalia Trotsky: letter re break with Fourth International and Socialist Workers Party, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Johnson-Forest: What We Are Leaving Behind, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - M. Pablo: The Building of the Revolutionary Party, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Internal Documents, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Internal Documents, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Club Executive Minutes, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Internal Documents, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Peng: Pabloism Reviewed, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Draft Resolutions: The Soviet Union Today [sect iv]; The Third Chinese Revolution and Its Aftermath [sect ii]; The Rise of the Colonial Bourgeoise [sect iii]; includes correspondence, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Digest of 1949 U.S. White Paper on China, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Club Executive Minutes, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Internal Documents, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Communications to National Committee Members, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - On the CPUSA, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Joseph Hansen: Report on the Trotsky School, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Draft Resolution: The World Today, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Draft Resolution on Stalinism, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Draft Resolution: The Crisis of Stalinism, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Draft Resolution on Middle East, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - re slogan, Federal Troops to Mississippi, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Internal Documents, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Tentative Outline for Political Report to Convention, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Young Socialist League (YSL): correspondence and reports, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Draft Resolution: Towards a Revolutionary Party in Britain; Suez and its Aftermath, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Club Executive Minutes, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Internal Documents, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Internal Documents, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Club Executive Minutes, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Revised Draft Political Resolution - regroupment, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Internal Documents, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - James Cannon: letter with 1945 "On The Party Press", 1960 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Raj Narain Arya: statements, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Political Committee Minutes, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Draft: Tasks and Perspectives Resolution; Tasks and Perspectives Resolution, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Murry Weiss: Memorandum on the Principled Groundwork of Our Tactics and Slogans in the Struggle Against Imperialist War, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Concerning Cuba, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Internal Documents, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Political Committee Minutes, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Pre Convention and 19th National Convention Minutes, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - National Executive Committee Minutes (with attached correspondence), 1961 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Monroe Defense Movement, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Internal Documents, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Political Committee Draft: Problems of the Fourth International And the Next Steps, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Draft Resolution: The Chinese Revolution: Its Character and Development, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Political Committee Minutes, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Internal Documents, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Political Committee Minutes, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - National Committee Plenum, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss: Plenum Speech, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Draft of Convention Resolution: Freedom Now, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Draft Resolution on the Organizational Character of the SWP, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Suspension of Robertson-Mage-White Minority Tendency: statements and correspondence, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Statement of the Reorganized Minority Tendency: The Decline of American Imperialism and the Tasks of the SWP, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Draft Resolution: Preparing for the Next Wave of Radicalism in the United States, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Draft Resolution: The SWP Position on China (May); The SWP Position on China with Wohlforth amendment (June), 1963 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Draft Resolution: The Sino-Soviet Dispute; Marxist Policy in the Sino-Soviet Dispute, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Internal Documents, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Political Committee Minutes, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - National Executive Committee Minutes, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - 21st National Convention Minutes, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Internal Documents, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Internal Documents, circa 1967 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Hildegarde Swabeck: resignation letter, circa 1967 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Internal Documents, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Internal Documents, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Series IV: Committee for a Revolutionary Socialist Party (CRSP), 1978-1981; 4
  This series documents Tanner Weiss's involvement with and the activities of the Committee for a Revolutionary Socialist Party (CRSP) in 1978-1981. It consists of meeting minutes, articles, circulars, and conference proceedings. CRSP was dedicated to reinstituting American Trotskyism.
  - Internal Documents, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Internal Documents, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Internal Documents, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Series V: Speeches and Writings, undated, 1955-1978; 5
  This series contains speeches and other writings by Murry Weiss and Myra Tanner Weiss. Murry's speeches are related to radical political upheaval in the 1950s-1970s and often include handwritten notes. Myra's speech is related to living under FBI surveillance.
  - Murry Weiss, 1955-1978 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Myra Tanner Weiss, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)